Guide to the James A. Healy Collection of Irish literature, 1870-1976
Department of Special Collections
- Ryan, Desmond
  - St. Patrick's Breastplate. Dundrum: Cuala Press [1920], Two copies, variant covers and coloring of initials.
    See also: Manuscripts Box 16 for 1912 edition.
- Sheil, Teresa
  - Poems. Dublin: Cuala Press. 1930., 3434
    One of 50 copies privately printed for Mrs. Sheil. Unopened. Handcolored floral decoration and handcolored initials on page 1.
- Symons, Arthur
  - The Romantic Movement in English Poetry. London: Constable. 1909.
    Signed and holograph quotation: Coleridge is never fantastic.
- Synge, John M.
  - Deirdre of the Sorrows. Dundrum: Cuala Press. 1910., 3320
    James A Healy from his friend W B Yeats July 30 1938
- Synge, John M.
  - My Wallet of Photographs. Edited by L. Stephens. Dublin: Dolmen. 1971.
- Synge, John M.
  - Poems and Translations. Dundrum: Cuala Press. 1909., 3319
    To James A Healy from W B Yeats Synge was the most characteristic genius of our movement & will grow greater with the passage of time.
- Synge, John M.
  - Poems and Translations. New York: Printed for John Quinn. 1909.
    One of 50 copies.
- Synge, John M.
  - Some letters of John M. Synge to Lady Gregory and W.B. Yeats. Selected by Ann Saddlemyer. Dublin: Cuala Press. 1971., 3417
    No. 258 of 500 copies. Unopened.
    Holograph note to Healy from Nora Niland, librarian of Sligo County Library and Museum, laid in, dated 7/21/71.
- Tagore, Rabindranath
  - The Post Office. Translated by Devabrata Mukerjea. Dundrum: Cuala Press. 1914.
    - COPY ONE:, 3329
      No. 383 of 400 copies. Unopened. E.C. Yeats' bookplate laid in.
      To James A Healy. When we published this book The Post Office had just been played by the Abbey Theatre.
    - COPY TWO:, 3330
      No. 371 of 400 copies. John Quinn's copy with his bookplate.
- Tate, Nathum
  - Dido and Aeneas. Dundrum: Cuala Press. [1913 Privately printed]
    E.C. Yeats' bookplate pasted inside cover.
- Thom, [no first name given]
  - Thom's Irish Who's Who. Dublin: Thom. 1923.
- Tolhurst, Rogers
  - In the Emperor's Garden and Other Poems. Dublin: Cuala Press. 1928.Printed for the author., 3433
    One of 50 copies. Unopened.
- Tynan, Katherine
  - Collected Poems. London: Macmillan. 1930., 4143
- Tynan, Katherine
  - Memories. London: Eveleigh, Nash and Grayson. 1924., 4144
- Tynan, Katherine
  - The Middle Years. London: Constable. 1916.
- Tynan, Katherine
  - Twenty-Five Years: Reminiscences. London: Smith, Elder. 1913.
- Tynan, Katherine
  - Twenty One Poems. Selected by W.B. Yeats. Dundrum: Dun Emer Press. 1907., 3316
    To James A Healy from W B Yeats July 1938
    Title page signed by W.B. Yeats.
    ALS laid in:
    Feb. 21st. 1902.
    Dear Sir, --
    Certainly!
    Very sincerely yours Katherine Tynan Hinkson
- Tynan, Katherine
  - The Wandering Years. London: Constable. 1922., 4142
- Walker, J. Crampton
  - Irish Life and Landscape. Dublin: Talbot. n.d.
- Walker, F. S. and Mathew, F.
  - Ireland. London: Block. 1912.
- Warren, M.J.
  - The Twig of Thorn. Boston: Baker. 1910.
- Wellesley, Dorothy
  - Beyond the Grave: Letters on Poetry to W.B. Yeats. [No place: privately printed] n.d.
- Yeats, Jack Butler
  - La La Noo. Dublin: Cuala Press. 1943., 3406
    No. 171 of 250 copies. Unopened.
    On free front endpaper original ink sketch, signed:
    Jack B Yeats Dublin May 1946
- [Yeats, Jack B.]
  - Jack B. Yeats: A Biography. By Hilary Pyle. London: Routledge & Kegan Paul. 1970.
    Inscribed to James o. Healy.
- [Yeats, Jack B.]
  - Jack Yeats: A centenary Exhibition. Introduction by James White. London: Martin Secker & Warburg. 1971.
- [Yeats, Jack B.]
  - Jack B. Yeats and His Family. Introduction by Hilary Pyle. Dublin: Irish Printers. [1971]
- [Yeats, Jack B.]
  - Jack B. Yeats: Early Watercolours. London: Waddington Galleries. 1961.
- [Yeats, Jack B.]
  - Exhibition Catalogue, Sligo County Library. 1963.
- Yeats, John Butler
  - Early Memories. Dundrum: [Cuala Press] 1923., 3348
    To my friend James A Healy
    There is much about my uncle George Pollexfen in this wise [?] & simple book. He was a fine story teller. Andrew Jameson told me that he once went to Sligo with him & soon after they got inot the train My uncle began a story & finished it at the exact moment when the train reached Sligo at end of four or five hours. Andrew Jameson said it had not a dull moment. I dare say it went through seven generations. George Pollexfen was a great judge of horses and raced them as advised by their horoscopes.
    W.B. Yeats' preface signed by him.
- Yeats, John Butler
  - Further Letters of John Butler Yeats. Selected by Lennox Robinson. Dundrum: Cuala Press. 1920., 3344
    One of 400 copies. Unopened. E.C. Yeats' bookplate laid in.
    To my friend James A Healy W B Yeats 1938
    On title page Lennox Robinson's signature.
    Colophon signed by printer: Elizabeth C. Yeats'.
- Yeats, John Butler
  - Passages from the Letters of John Butler Yeats. Selected by Ezra Pound. Dundrum: Cuala Press. 1917., 3338
    To James A Healy Extracts from letters many or wholly to me. My father wrote whenever an idea came into his head. I seldome commented. I found that if I commented it checked the flow of his thought. W B Yeats 1938
- Yeats, Lily
  - Elizabeth Corbet Yeats. Born March 11th. 1868. Died January 16th. 1940. [Dublin: Cuala Press 1940]
    Lily Yeats' bookplate tipped into each copy.
    - COPY ONE:
      Inscribed in each individual's hand on last page of text:
      For James Healy a good friend to my sister myself & Cuala Lily Yeats Dundrum Co Dublin Ireland. July 7th 1940
      Esther Ryan
      Maire Gill
      Eileen Colum
      Kathleen Banfield
    - COPY TWO:
      Inscribed by Lily Yeats on last page of text:
      For James Healy the friend who helped and encouraged my sister over her work at Cuala Press, & who's sympathy on her death in January 1940 I am very grateful for Lily Yeats
    - COPY THREE:
      [In Manuscripts Box 16, Folder 257, q. v.]
- Yeats, William Butler
  - The Bounty of Sweden. Dublin: Cuala Press. 1925.
    - COPY ONE:, 3354
      One of 400 copies. Unopened. E. C. Yeats' bookplate laid in.
      at the end of my lecture to the Royal Swedish Academy I spoke of Lady Gregory `as sinking into the infirmety of age'. Lady Gregory saw some report & when I got home was so full of scorn at the idea of having any infirmities that I had to alter the phrase into its present form & put `vigerous old age'
      Author's signature on title page; his printed name crossed out.
    - COPY TWO:, 3355
      Lennox Robinson's copy with his bookplate.
- Yeats, William Butler
  - The cat and the moon and certain poems. Dublin: Cuala Press. 1924.
    One of 500 copies.
    - COPY ONE:, 3352
      Lennox Robinson's copy with his bookplate. Inscribed by Yeats on margins around the bookplate:
      May-1924- `Call down a blessing on the blossom of the may, Because it blows in beauty and in beauty blows away' W B Y
    - COPY TWO:, 3353
      The end of `the cat and the moon' is feeble in this book, but I have improved it & enlarged it, & now it plays very well.
- Yeats, William Butler
  - Discoveries: A Volume of Essays. Dundrum: Dun Emer Press. 1907., 3317
    One of 200 copies. Unopened. E. C. Yeats' bookplate laid in. Inscribed on first front flyleaf:
    To my friend James A Healy W B Yeats, July 30, 1938.
    W B Yeats, Dec 16 1907. `banjo' on page 10 is a slip of the pen for `guitar'
    Yes a `slip' though not of the pen - probably from ignorance. The player was the Countess of Cromarty. W B Y 1938
- Yeats, William Butler
  - The Death of Synge, and Other Passages from an Old Diary. Dublin: Cuala Press. 1928., 3360
    For James A Healy Perhaps my best prose book W B Yeats 1938
- Yeats, William Butler
  - Dramatis personae. Dublin: Cuala Press. 1935.
    - COPY ONE:, 3377
      One of 400 copies. Elizabeth C. Yeats' bookplate laid in.
      The last section of my biography that has been published. It will be difficult to continue for I have come to the people who will outlive me. W B Yeats July 5 1938
    - COPY TWO:, 3378
      Lennox Robinson's copy with his bookplate, dated in his hand: November 1935.
- Yeats, William Butler
  - Essays by W.B. Yeats, 1931 to 1936. Dublin: Cuala Press. 1937., 3381
    One of 300 copies. Elizabeth C. Yeats' bookplate laid in. Unopened.
    For James A Healy from his friend W B Yeats On turning over these pages I find they are often difficult, remote from general interest as if I were talking to myself as indeed I was. Of late I have changed & hence forth my friend[s] find me intelligible though more extravagant. Gradually one grows into certainty. W B Yeats 1938
- Yeats, William Butler
  - Estrangement. Dublin: Cuala Press. 1926., 3357
    When I wrote these essays I was working at the Abbey Theatre. Fay had gone I think & I was over worked or my nerves were. That is why there are some sour paragraphs
- Yeats, William Butler
  - Four Years. Dundrum: Cuala Press. 1921.
    - COPY ONE:, 3346
      The design on the title page was by T. Sturge Moore a distinguished poet & designer & a good friend of mine.
    - COPY TWO:, 3346a
      Lennox Robinson's bookplate on free front end-paper; Christmas - 1921 written on bookplate.
- Yeats, William Butler
  - The Green Helmet and Other Poems. Dundrum: Cuala Press. 1910., 3321
    One of 400 copies. Unopened. Erratum slip laid in. E. C. Yeats' bookplate laid in.
    James A Healy from W B Yeats The Cuchulain myth was the myth of that time. Standish O'Grady had started it. Padraic Pearse was inspired by it, a fact commemorated by the statue of Cuchulain in the rebuilt Post office July 1938
- Yeats, William Butler
  - The Hour Glass. Dundrum: Cuala Press. 1914.[Privately printed], 3428 in portfolio
    Case 16:B/2
    Inscribed by Lily Yeats on verso of front cover:
    This is my bookplate drawn for me by my brother Jack -- the metal sailor stands at the mouth of the river at Rosses Point Sligo. his twin stands on shore at Tramore Waterford -- we as children thought a great deal of him, & still admire him.
    Lily Yeats
    Inscribed by W. B. Yeats on title page:
    This little book was published privately by John Quinn, to save American copyright. Since then I have greatly altered the end of the play. W B Yeats
    Inscribed by Lily Yeats on verso of titlepage:
    It is pleasant to know that this small book now belongs to Willy's good friend James A. Healy -- Lily Yeats
    Lily Yeats' bookplate laid in.
- Yeats, William Butler
  - If I were Four-And-Twenty. Dublin: Cuala Press. 1940.
    - COPY ONE:, 3396
      No. 308 of 450 copies. Unopened.
      Inscribed for James A. Healy, friend of W B Y and George Yeats. George Yeats December 1946
    - COPY TWO:, 3397
      No. 309 of 450 copies. Unopened.
      Inscribed for James A. Healy by George Yeats
- Yeats, William Butler
  - In the Seven Woods. Dundrum: Dun Emer Press. 1903.
    - COPY ONE:, 3300
      One of 325 copies. Uncut. E.C. Yeats' bookplate laid in.
      To James A Healy The paper in this book & other early books published by my sister was made from an old receipt supplied by that famous printer, the greatest modern master of this craft Emery Walker. Today we cannot get anybody to make it. W B Yeats July 1938
      Inscription by printer after colophon:
      This book took us -- (Esther Ryan and I --) six months to print, but it was exciting. E. Ryan was only fifteen. Just left school -- Elizabeth C Yeats
    - COPY TWO:, 3301
      Uncut. John Quinn's copy with his bookplate.
      This is the first book of mine that it is a pleasure to look at -- a pleasure whether open or shut. W B Yeats. March 1904
- Yeats, William Butler
  - The king of the great clock tower. Dublin: Cuala Press. 1934., 3376
    For James A Healy I have since re-written The King of the Clock Tower in verse. Ninnette de Valois played and danced magnificently in this prose version. The great dancer with a strange tragic face injured a foot some years ago & must arrange dances instead of dancing. She can however sometimes dance in a short piece like this. I found her dancers at Cambridge years ago when she and they were little known & asked her to open a School of Ballet in Dublin & dance for me there. W B Yeats July 5 1938.
- Yeats, William Butler
  - Last Poems and Two Plays. Dublin: Cuala Press. 1939.
    - COPY ONE:, 3388
      One of 500 copies. Unopened. Elizabeth C. Yeats bookplate laid in.
      To James A. Healy Whose great kindness to my brother - and warm interest in my work here at the Cuala Press I will always remember with gratitude Elizabeth C Yeats July 21 1939
    - COPY TWO:, 3389
      Unopened. Elizabeth C. Yeats' bookplate laid in.
      To James A. Healy through whose untiring kindness many of the poems in this book were written in the South of France: George Yeats
      Colophon signed by printer: Elizabeth Corbet Yeats. July 1939.
- Yeats, William Butler
  - Letters to the New Island. Edited by Horace Reynolds. Cambridge, Mass.: Harvard University Press. 1934., 4199
    Case [UNK]
- Yeats, William Butler
  - Michael Robartes and The Dancer. Dundrum: Cuala Press. 1920., 3345
    I am not proud of the prose parts of this book. They are thoroughly bad, & have been superceded by a book of mine called A Vision W B Yeats 1938
    Colophon signed by printer: Elizabeth C Yeats
- Yeats, William Butler
  - Modern Poetry. The Eighteenth Broadcast National Lecture. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press. 1936.
- Yeats, William Butler
  - Mosada. Dublin: Cuala Press. 1943.Privately printed.
    - COPY ONE:, 3440
      No. 25 of 50 copies.
      For James A. Healy friend of W B Yeats from George Yeats
    - COPY TWO:, 3441
      No. 26 of 50 copies.
      To my friend James A. Healy with greetings from George Yeats
    - COPY THREE:, 3442
      No. 27 of 50 copies.
      To James A. Healy with best wishes from George Yeats
- Yeats, William Butler
  - New Poems. Dublin: Cuala Press. 1938.
    - COPY ONE:, 3383
      One of 450 copies. Unopened. Elizabeth C. Yeats' bookplate laid in.
      Politics
      `In our time the destiny of man presents its meaning in political terms.' Thomas Mann
      Beside the window stands a girl; I cannot fix my mind On their analysis of things That benumb mankind. Yet one has travelled and may know What he talks about, And one's a politician That has read & thought; Maybe what they say is true Of war and war's alarm, But O that I were young again And held her in my arms.
      W B Yeats, May 24 [1938]
      I finished this yesterday if it is finished
      Laid in clipping from Atlantic Monthly, January, 1939, with final version of Politics.
    - COPY TWO:, 3384
      For James A Healy Pater told a friend of his that he thought his last book Plato & Platonism more natural in its style than any other book of his. This is my most natural book. W B Yeats 1938
- Yeats, William Butler
  - October blast. Dublin: Cuala Press. 1927., 3359
    One of 350 copies. Unopened. E.C. Yeats' bookplate laid in.
    `The Tower' describes my own old Town in Co Galway Thoor Ballylee or rather its neighborhood. Mrs. French lived a couple of miles off in the eighteenth century.
- Yeats, William Butler
  - On the Boiler. Dublin: Cuala Press. [ 1939Unlimited edition]
    E.C. Yeats' bookplate laid in.
    - COPY ONE:, 3421
      Inscribed on half title:
      James A. Healy in grateful remembrance of his great friendship & kindness to my brother W.B. Yeats -- and his steady support of my work here at Cuala Elizabeth C Yeats September 7. 1939
    - COPY TWO:, 3422
      Inscribed on half title by George Yeats and E.C. Yeats
      To my friend James A. Healy with grateful appreciation of his many kindnesses, from George Yeats
      Published by Elizabeth C. Yeats at the Cuala Press August 1939
- Yeats, William Butler
  - A Packet for Ezra Pound. Dublin: Cuala Press. 1929., 3362
    One of 425 copies. Unopened. E. C. Yeats' bookplate laid in.
    A part of my philosophical book a Vision published in its final form last year.
    W B Yeats. 1938
- Yeats, William Butler
  - Pages from a Diary Written in Nineteen Hundred and Thirty. Dublin: Cuala Press. 1944., 3410
    No. 225 of 280 copies. Unopened.
    Inscribed for James A. Healy, friend and helper of W.B. Yeats, by George Yeats
- Yeats, William Butler
  - Plates to Accompany `Reveries over Childhood and Youth'. Dundrum: Cuala Press. 1915., 3334
    The portfolio contains portraits of John Butler Yeats and his wife from drawings by himself, and a color reproduction of a watercolor, `Memory Harbour', by Jack B. Yeats, with a note by W.B. Yeats printed on a single sheet.
    E.C. Yeats' inscription on John Butler Yeats' portrait:
    We don't think our father ever did justice to his appearance on his self portrait -- still, this is like himself but giving no idea of how handsome a man he was ----
    On Susan Yeats' picture:
    This pen & ink sketch of my Mother was done a few years after her marriage.
    Elizabeth C. Yeats
    On W.B. Yeats' note:
    Yes -- this is Rosses Point Sligo --- I too see it in my mind's eye as Jack has made it in his picture
    Elizabeth C Yeats
- Yeats, William Butler
  - Poe`mes. Translated by A. Audra. Paris: Éditions du Vieux Colombier. 1956.
- Yeats, William Butler
  - Poems. Dublin: Cuala Press. 1935.Privately printed for Lady Eleanor Yarrow., 3438
    One of 30 copies.
    Handcolored frontispiece, and freehand painted initials and small decorations through [by E.C. Yeats]
    E.C. Yeats' bookplate tipped in.
- Yeats, William Butler
  - Poems Written in Discouragement, 1912-1913. Cuala Press. Dundrum. 1913., 3427 in portfolio
    Lily Yeats' bookplate pasted in.
    This Bookplate was designed for me by my brother Jack when I was a girl -- the sailor is set at the mouth of the river at Rosses Point Sligo, he was put there about 1822, & with outstretched hand points to the deep water -- he reads a book only for me -- Lily Yeats
    At foot of p. 1:
    I am glad that this little book belonging to my sister Lily is going to my friend James A. Healy. These poems were written when the Dublin corporation had refused the gallery Hugh Lane asked for, the most influential member of this corporation heaping abuse on Lane. Since Lane's death the corporation has made amends. W B Yeats
- Yeats, William Butler and Johnson, Lionel
  - Poetry and Ireland. Dundrum: Cuala Press. 1908.No notice of limitation., 3318
    To James A. Healy from W B Yeats I think the second essay, that by Lionel Johnson, was a lecture before the National Literary Society in Dublin. July 30, 1938
    Colophon signed by the printer: Elizabeth C Yeats.
- Yeats, William Butler
  - Reflections. Transcribed and edited by Curtis Bradford from the journals. Dublin: Cuala Press. 1970., 3416
    No. 428 of 500 copies. Unopened.
- Yeats, William Butler
  - Responsibilities. Dundrum: Cuala Press. 1914.
    - COPY ONE:, 3327
      No. 360 of 400 copies. Unopened. E.C. Yeats' bookplate laid in.
      To James A Healy from W B Yeats, 1938
      I made my song a coat Covered with embroideries Out of old mythologies From heel to throat; But the fools caught it, Wore it in the world's eye As though they'd wrought it. Song, let them take it For there's more enterprise In walking naked.
      Title page signed by author.
    - COPY TWO:, 3328
      No. 366 of 400 copies.
      Hilda Dowden's copy with her bookplate. Unopened.
- Yeats, William Butler
  - Reveries Over Childhood and Youth. Dundrum: Cuala Press. 1915.
    - COPY ONE:, 3333
      No. 334 of 425 copies. Unopened. E.C. Yeats' bookplate laid in.
      James A. Healy from his friend W B Yeats. I meant to call this book Memory Harbour from a picture of that name by my brother. But found at the last moment that somebody else had seen the picture & taken the name. W B Y July 30. 1938
    - COPY TWO:, 3335
      No. 304 of 425 copies. Unopened.
      To James A Healy, the friend o my friend John Quinn W B Yeats, August 15, 1937
      See also: Plates to Accompany `Reveries Over Childhood and Youth'.
- Yeats, William Butler
  - A Selection from the Love Poetry of William Butler Yeats. Dundrum: Cuala Press. 1913., 3324
    Inscribed by author:
    James A Healy from his friend W B Yeats. July 30 1938
- Yeats, William Butler
  - Seven Poems and a Fragment. Dundrum: Cuala Press. 1922., 3347
    One of 500 copies. E.C. Yeats' bookplate laid in.
    Inscribed by author on page [xi]:
    I think the poem called `Thoughts upon the present state of the world' was the first poem in what crities call my `later manner'. It was written when the Black & Tans were busy, and their actions more than anything at the time had plunged me into gloom. Before this I had written of old Myths & personal passion
- Yeats, William Butler
  - A Speech and Two Poems. Dublin: Sign of the Three Candles. 1937., 3479
    No. 18 of 70 copies.
    Inscribed on title page:
    James A. Healy from W B Yeats with gratitude & thanks
- Yeats, William Butler
  - Stories of Michael Robartes and his Friends. Dublin: Cuala Press. 1931., 3369
    One of 450 copies. Unopened. E.C. Yeats' bookplate laid in.
    For James A Healy Part of my philosophical book A vision. I have improved the stories since and added a new one
- Yeats, William Butler
  - Stories of Red Hanrahan. Dundrum: Dun Emer Press. 1904.
    - COPY ONE:, 3305
      Inscribed by author on halftitle:
      Inscribed for James A Healy The friend was Lady Gregory. The not very successful design on the next page was by her son not yet master of design he soon became.
    - COPY TWO:, 3306
      Inscriptions by Lily Yeats on flyleaf:
      To FitzRoy Carrington from Lily Yeats New York May 19th 1908
- Yeats, William Butler
  - Synge and the Ireland of His Time. With a Note Concerning a Walk through Connemara with Him by Jack Butler Yeats. Dundrum: Cuala Press. 1911., 3322
    To James A Healy from W B Yeats July 1938 Synge and my brother loved one another, both had long silences & a walk through Connemara gave them much opportunity. Synge said of himself `almost forgetting human words'
    Preface signed by author.
    Jack Yeats' contribution is signed by him with a small ink drawing.
    Colophon signed by printer: Elizabeth Corbet Yeats.
- Yeats, William Butler
  - Two plays for Dancers. Dundrum: Cuala Press. 1919., 3342
    I made a different version of this second play more suitable to the ordinary stage. It permits the use of many dancers. That great dancer Ninnette de Valois came to Ireland & danced for us
- Yeats, William Butler
  - The Wild Swans at Coole. Dundrum: Cuala Press. 1917., 3339
    The poems headed `To a dying Lady' are about Mabel Beardsley, the sister of the artist. She died of cancer. A number of her friends took an afternoon each that she might always, if she wished, have a visitor. She was an heroic person. She always managed to seem well. If any body had a cold she never failed to ask after it. I did not see her at the very end. I was in Ireland.
    Colophon signed by printer: Elizabeth C. Yeats - [illegible word in Gaelic?]
- Yeats, William Butler
  - The Wind Among the Reeds. London: Elkin Mathews. 1899., 3481
    Inside front cover Lily Yeats' bookplate and her inscription:
    This fine sailor is made of iron & stands by the Rosses Point - Sligo - not reading but pointing to where deep water is behind him are rocks & shallow water, he was put up about 1822 - & wears the dress of sailors of that time - Lily Yeats
    Inscriptions on first flyleaf:
    The cover for this book was designed by an Irish artist whose family was so stuck up that the neighbors called them `the Royal Family. I have not seen her for many years. I do not know whether she is living or not. W B Yeats